{"tossups": [{"question": "One of this character's friends sees a man spitting off a bridge and immediately hires that man, Planchet, to be this character's servant. This character is shot in the throat at Maastricht and dies shortly after receiving a promotion. He develops a rivalry with the \"Man from Meung,\" who steals his introduction letter and is revealed to be the Comte de (*) Rochefort. He and his landlord's wife Constance Bonancieux convey diamonds from the Queen to the Duke of Buckingham, despite the interference of Milady de Winter. This character's namesake romances include the novel The Vicomte de Bragelonne, which ends with The Man in the Iron Mask. For 10 points, name this character who befriends Athos, Porthos and Aramis in The Three Musketeers.", "answer": "D'Artagnan [or Charles Ogier de Batz de Castelmore, Comte d'Artagnan]", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This composer created a \"mike tone\" by having the trombone play above the clarinet for a song he composed with Benny Bigard. At the 1956 Newport Jazz Festival, Paul Gonsalves played a solo for 27 choruses during one of this composer's songs, reviving his career. This composer of \"Diminuendo and Crescendo in Blue\" and (*) \"Sophisticated Lady\" featured Johnny Hodges and Juan Tizol in his band, whose signature tune was co-written with Billy Strayhorn. His orchestra played at the Cotton Club from 1927 to 1931, performing standards such as his \"Mood Indigo.\" For 10 points, name this pianist and bandleader who wrote the standards \"Take the A Train\" and \"It Don't Mean a Thing (If It Ain't Got That Swing).\"", "answer": "Edward Kennedy \"Duke\" Ellington", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In spectroscopy, thermal motion of particles causes line broadening via this effect. Within an optical trap, this effect can be used to cool atoms; that setup is used to create Bose-Einstein condensates. At relativistic speeds, this effect's namesake factor is the Lorenz gamma times the quantity one minus v divided by the speed of light. Special relativity predicts a transverse version of it. At lower speeds, the wave (*) velocity is added or subtracted from the receiver or source speed in the numerator and denominator, respectively, of the factor multiplying the frequency. For 10 points, identify this effect in which the relative motion of the emitter and observer causes a shift in the observed frequency of a wave.", "answer": "Doppler effect", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The concept of \"deferred action\" was used to explain away the horribly botched facial surgery endured by one of these figures. Another of them was a Russian emigrant whose name derived from the stark-white figures he observed in a tree outside his window. One of these figures witnessed a carriage overturn in a park, leading his reactions to clattering noises to be bizarrely blamed on large horse (*) genitalia. These individuals included the \"Wolf Man,\" a boy called \"Little Hans,\" and Anna O., and they were used to illustrate concepts like repression, castration anxiety, and thanatos by the author of Civilization and its Discontents and The Interpretation of Dreams. For 10 points, name these figures who were treated and used as case studies by the Austrian founder of psychoanalysis.", "answer": "patients of Sigmund Freud [accept all reasonable equivalents like \"clients,\" \"subjects,\" \"case studies,\" etc. as long as the answer has Freud in it; accept The Interpretation of Dreams or just Sigmund Freud before \"these figures\"]", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "An attempt to tax fruit by this city's Spanish rulers led to the rebellion of Masaniello. A later rebellion here involved this city liberating itself from Nazi occupation in a namesake \"four days.\" This city, where the rulers were supported by the lower-class Lazzaroni, was where Emma Hamilton met Horatio Nelson during Nelson's mission against the (*) Parthenopean Republic here. Later in the Napoleonic era, this home of the Camorra was ruled by Joseph Bonaparte and Joachim Murat. This target of Garibaldi's Expedition of the Thousand was the seat of the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. For 10 points, name this Italian city in the environs of Vesuvius.", "answer": "Naples [or Napoli]", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This god's daughter once used a love charm to make Io fall in love with Zeus and was transformed into a wryneck as punishment. This god swore off all clothes after being kicked by Hercules, who was dressed as Omphale, out of their bedroom. He spread his namesake frenzy among a group of shepherds, who tore Echo limb from limb after she ran away from this god. In a contest judged by Timolus, (*) Midas grew ass's ears by ruling in favor of this god against Apollo. River nymphs transformed his love interest Syrinx into some reeds, from which this god fashioned a musical instrument. He is equated with the Roman Faunus, had goat legs, and loved to play the pipes. For 10 points, name this son of Hermes, a satyr.", "answer": "Pan [or Faunus before mentioned]", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "Jerry Pournelle wrote, \"it's raining soup, and [this politician] has the blueprints for soup bowls\" in his preface to this man's manifesto \"Window of Opportunity.\" This man praised zoos in A Nation Like No Other and chronicled Pope John Paul II's role in ending communism in the film Nine Days that Changed the World. Attack ads against this man by Restore Our Future used footage from a global warming commercial he made with Nancy Pelosi. He produced two (*) Restoring God in America films with his wife Callista, and he has been attacked for serving as an advisor for Freddie Mac. For 10 points, name this unsuccessful candidate for the Republican nomination who was once Speaker of the House.", "answer": "Newton Leroy \"Newt\" Gingrich [or Newton Leroy McPherson]", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "In one novel set in this city, the title character eyes a woman who reminds him of his dead wife Minna Davis during an earthquake. Post Office, Factotum, and Ham on Rye are among the works about a native of this city named Henry Chinaski. The \"Burning\" of this city is painted by Tod Hackett, who befriends Homer Simpson in another novel set in this city. Kathleen Moore become the mistress of (*) Monroe Stahr in another novel set here. This setting of Nathanael West's The Day of the Locust is also the home of Philip Marlowe, who appears in The Big Sleep. For 10 points, name this city home to Charles Bukowski, also the setting of F. Scott Fitzgerald's The Last Tycoon, which centers on a movie executive in Hollywood.", "answer": "Los Angeles, California [or L.A.; accept Hollywood until it is read]", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This country was home to the city of Cuscatla\u0301n, built by the Pipil people. The dissatisfaction of indigo planters led men like Manuel Jose Acre and Jose Matias Delgado to organize an independence movement in this nation. The Fourteen Families in this country presided over its switch to a coffee economy. Men like Jose Maria Lemus and Oscar Osorio took power here in the Majors' Revolution, and it fought its eastern neighbor in the (*) Soccer War. The assassination of Archbishop Oscar Romero sparked a civil war in this country in the 1980s. For 10 points, fighting between Jose Napoleon Duarte and the FMLN occurred in what small Central American country?", "answer": "El Salvador", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Some cells in this organ develop from the ultimobrachial body, and dysgenesis of this organ is linked to Pax8 mutations. This organ descends through the foramen cecum during development. Granulomas appear in this organ in De Quervain's disease. In another disease, anti-peroxidase antibodies attack this organ. Exophthalmos, or eye-popping, is a symptom of overstimulation of this organ, whose main product is cleaved from colloid and is secreted by (*) follicular cells. C cells in this organ secrete a peptide that opposes the action of PTH, called calcitonin. The main product of this organ is created by fusing two molecules of tyrosine together and adding iodine, which is why iodine deficiency causes goiter. For 10 points, name this gland in the neck.", "answer": "thyroid", "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This author wrote a story hinging on the Zhuangzi-esque question of whether a victim of a motorcycle accident dreams he is a Moteca Indian, or vice-versa. In another story by this author of \"The Night Face-Up,\" Roberto Michel sees a middle-aged woman trying to seduce a young boy in an old photograph he took. That story, \"Las Babas del Diablo\", was adapted into Michelangelo (*) Antonioni's film Blow-Up. The infant Rocamadour dies in his most famous novel, which describes Serpent Club member Horacio Oliveira's search for La Maga and begins with a \"Table of Instructions\" on how to proceed through its chapters, 99 of which are \"expendable\". For 10 points, name this Argentine author of Rayuela, or Hopscotch.", "answer": "Julio Cortazar [or Jules Florencio Cortazar]", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "One of these pieces begins with a melody whose series of dissonant minor seconds make it seem like the pianist is playing the wrong notes. In the second of these pieces, the right hand's third, fourth, and fifth fingers play rapid chromatic passages. They are collected in their composer's Opus 10 and Opus 25, and include pieces nicknamed \"Ocean\" and (*) \"Winter Wind.\" They were the first piano pieces of their type to become concert pieces rather than simple technical challenges. The twelfth of them was inspired by an 1830 uprising in their composer's home country and is nicknamed \"Revolutionary.\" For 10 points, name these studies for piano written by a Romantic Polish composer.", "answer": "Frederic Chopin's etudes [prompt on partial answer; prompt on Frederic \"Chopin's studies\", \"studies\", or equivalents]", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The OSCAR dataset maps these entities, which are responsible for mixing isopynic parcels via cabbeling. Stommel showed that their \"westward intensification\" was due to gradients in the Coriolis force. The total flux due to these phenomena is measured in Sverdrups. One driving force for them is variations in temperature and salt concentration; those differences drive (*) upwellings and downwellings. Wind forcing results in net transport via these entities at 90 degrees to the wind direction, a process called Ekman transport. Sediment buildup causes the \"turbidity\" type of these entities. Examples of another form of these entities include the Kuroshio, North Equatorial, and Antarctic circumpolar. For 10 points, name these flows of water through the Earth's oceans.", "answer": "oceanic currents [accept oceanic circulation; prompt on \"flow\" or \"ocean flow\"; prompt on anything that implies water is moving]", "subcategory": "Science Other", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A \"pseudo-\" version of this author is known as \"the Old Oligarch.\" One of his works has a section about the fictional King Abradatas and tells of how its subject diverted a river to attack Babylon. Another of his works has an episode in which the protagonists cry \"Thalatta! Thalatta!\" after finding the Black Sea. One of his works was an early example of the \"mirrors for princes\" genre, a biography entitled the (*) Cyropaedia. Another of his works details how several officers were killed after going to Tissaphernes' feast, and how the protagonists won the Battle of Cunaxa on behalf of Cyrus the Younger. For 10 points, name this historian who detailed the Expedition of the Ten Thousand in his Anabasis.", "answer": "Xenophon", "subcategory": "Literature Classical", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "On one holy day honoring this figure, followers offer bael-tree leaves and cold water, or draw three stripes of ash across their foreheads to commemorate the digging of the Well of Wisdom, or Jnana Vapi, in his holiest temple. This deity detected a fellow god's lie about reaching the end of an infinitely-tall tower of fire, since he was actually the tower, and removed the fifth (*) head from that liar, Brahma. Often depicted crushing a dwarf with one foot in the air, he is worshiped using stump-like structures called lingams. Though not Neptune, he wears a crescent moon in his matted hair and wields a trident. For 10 points, name this consort of Parvati who can incinerate others by opening his third eye, a Hindu Trumurti member and destroyer god.", "answer": "Shiva [accept Siva; accept Maha Shivaratri until \"this figure\" is read]", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "This poet wonders \"what made fatuous sunbeams toil / To break earth's sleep at all?\" in a work beginning \"Move him into the sun.\" The speaker of another of his poems asks, \"What candles may be held to speed them all?\" before asserting that the \"holy glimmers of goodbyes\" will shine \"not in the hands of boys but in their eyes.\" This poet of \"Futility\" described the \"shrill, demented choirs of wailing (*) shells\" in a sonnet that asks \"What passing-bells for these who die as cattle?\" In another poem, he wrote of an \"ecstasy of fumbling\" prompted by a gas attack which left a man \"guttering, choking, drowning.\" For 10 points, name this poet of \"Anthem for Doomed Youth\" who decried \"the old Lie\" in \"Dulce et Decorum Est\" and died in World War I.", "answer": "Wilfred Edward Salter Owen", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "In his work in this discipline, Aristotle considered a sea battle that happened in the distant past in formulating his own \"master argument.\" Another work in this field analyzes the doctrines of being, essence, and concept. Residues and concomitant variations are two of five of Mill's methods in this field. The creation of possible worlds by adding qualifiers, like adding the word \"usually\" to \"Eric is sad,\" is the province of the (*) \"modal\" form of it. One law in this field postulates the excluded middle. DeMorgan's laws apply to the operators in this field, which uses a construction made up of a major premise, a minor premise, and a conclusion. For 10 points, name this field of philosophy that uses the syllogism and is concerned with deductive reasoning.", "answer": "logic [accept word forms]", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "One member of this group went on to found the Death Valley Chamber of Commerce. Their targets included a man who was trying to sell a used radio, Steven Parent; the heir to the Folger Coffee fortune; and hair stylist Jay Sebring. A different member of this group was, along with Sarah Jane Moore, one of two women who attempted to (*) assassinate Gerald Ford in 1975. This group was exposed when Susan Atkins bragged about their killings to another inmate and was put on trial in a 1970 spectacle which included Lynette Fromme protesting outside the courthouse with swastikas carved into her forehead. For 10 points, name this cult which found secret messages in Beatles songs, especially \"Helter Skelter,\" and killed actress Sharon Tate in 1969, among eight others.", "answer": "the Family [or the Manson Family; or the Mansons]", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This artist painted a dwarf with extra-long fingers named Achille Emperaire. This artist of Pyramid of Skulls placed apples around an armless statue in his Still Life with Cherub. A man in a black coat with his back to the viewer looks at a nude and her black servant in a work exhibited alongside this man's House of the Hanged Man. Besides A (*) Modern Olympia, he painted trees forming a triangle above a group of nude women in The Large Bathers. He also executed numerous versions of Card Players. He painted several landscapes of a mountain visible from his house in Provence. For 10 points, name this French post-impressionist and proto-cubist fond of painting Mont Sainte-Victoire.", "answer": "Paul Cezanne", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This substance comes in \"white fuming\" and \"red fuming\" varieties at 16 molar concentration. It is commonly mixed with water at 68% concentration, at which it forms an azeotrope. Modern methods of producing pure forms of this strong oxidizing agent involve dehydrating the product with sulfuric acid and bubbling the reactant through hydrogen peroxide instead of water. Its large-scale production is done by mixing five equivalents of diatomic oxygen with four equivalents of (*) ammonia in the presence of a platinum/rhodium catalyst in the Ostwald process. Its pKa is approximately negative 1, and mixing it with hydrochloric acid gives aqua regia. For 10 points, name this compound with formula HNO3, a very strong acid.", "answer": "nitric acid [accept HNO3 or nitrate before mention; prompt after]", "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This man names a phenomenon that charged particles undergo when repeatedly reflected by a magnetic mirror, his namesake acceleration. In a semiconductor, he names the energy of the highest occupied quantum state. The probability of a quantum eigenstate transition is given by his \"Golden Rule\". This man's theory of beta decay posited the creation of a neutrino via the weak force. With (*) Dirac, this scientist names the distribution followed by particles of half-integer spin, which also carry his name. This man discovered several new elements by irradiation with slow neutrons, and he names element number 100. For 10 points, name this Italian physicist who created the first self-sustaining nuclear chain reaction and participated in the Manhattan Project.", "answer": "Enrico Fermi", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In one battle in this war, James Hope Grant's forces captured the Eight-Mile Bridge, and in another, the USS San Jacinto destroyed the Pearl River Forts. One side intervened in this war due to the execution of August Chapdelaine. Lord Elgin burned the Summer Palaces during this conflict. After this conflict, the Office of Foreign Affairs was created as part of the (*) Self-Strengthening Movement by Prince Gong. This conflict began after a Red Ensign was taken down after the Arrow was boarded, which violated the Treaty of Nanking. For 10 points, name this conflict between China and a British-French alliance, the second in a series of conflicts to ensure a certain narcotic could be exported.", "answer": "Second Opium War [prompt on \"Opium War\" till \"second\", accept after; accept Second Anglo-Chinese War or Second China War before \"China\", prompt after; accept Arrow War till \"Arrow\", prompt after; accept Anglo-French expedition to China till \"China\", prompt after]", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This character is forced to manage a garden for two years before escaping his enslavement by the Sale\u0301 Rovers with the boy Xury. After this character discovers in Lisbon that he has accrued a fortune from Mr. Wells profitably managing his sugar plantation in Brazil, he crosses the Pyrenees, where he is attacked by wolves during a snowstorm. This character convinces a man who worships (*) Benamuckee to call him \"master.\" He meets a parrot named Poll and discovers a mysterious single footprint in a place dubbed \"Despair\" and found near the mouth of the Orinoco. While on that island, this character fights off cannibals with the help of Friday. For 10 points, name this Alexander Selkirk-inspired stranded sailor, the title character of a Daniel Defoe novel.", "answer": "Robinson Crusoe [accept either underlined portion]", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This leader is tricked into signing a peace treaty with the Gibeonites and orders the execution of Achan for illegally taking plunder. He is commanded to hold out his javelin towards the city of Ai, a sign that the city will fall into his people's hands. Along with Caleb, he is the only scout to give a positive report regarding the invasion of (*) Canaan. This leader sent in spies to one city, where they met a prostitute named Rahab. In one battle, this man defeated the Amorites after praying for the sun to stand still. He instructed his priests to blow trumpets during his defeat of Jericho. For 10 points, name this man, whose namesake book describes his leadership of the Israelites after Moses.", "answer": "Joshua [or Y'hoshua or Hoshea]", "category": "Religion"}], "bonuses": [{"leadin": "This phylum's members alternate between a motile medusa stage and a sessile polyp stage, and during development they only have two germ layers bound by a mesoglea. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["cnidarians", "mesoderm", "Xenopus laevis [or X laevis or African clawed frog; prompt on \"frog\"]"], "parts": ["Name this phylum of simple animals which includes hydras, jellyfish, and sea anemones.", "Cnidarians lack this middle germ layer, which in humans is sandwiched between the ectoderm and endoderm and develops into the connective tissues and muscles of the body.", "A common model organism used to study development is this amphibian, which is useful due to its large oocytes. The gray crescent appears on the dorsal side of its embryo during gastrulation."], "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"leadin": "This symphony calls for eight trumpets, eight French horns, seven trombones, three different choirs, and an organ. For 10 points each:", "answers": ["SYMPHONY OF A THOUSAND", "MAHLER", "CELESTA"], "parts": ["Name this symphony, whose second part is based on the final scene from Faust, Part Two. It begins with a setting of the hymn \"Veni, creator spiritus", "The \"Symphony of a Thousand\" was written by this Austrian composer of The Song of the Earth, whose second symphony is nicknamed \"Resurrection.\"", "Mahler's score also calls for this keyboard instrument that produces sound by striking metal bars. Tchaikovsky featured it in his \"Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy.\""], "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}]}